Guide to the George Y. Shevelov Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Correspondence, 1950-2001
  - Subseries I.2: Correspondence with Organizations, 1951-2001
    - "Stezhky kul'tury", New York, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Student:hazeta ukrains'koho studenstva Kanady, Edmonton, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Svedectvi, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Svito-vyd, Lexington, NY, 1991 1997 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Svitovyi Kongress Ukraintsiv, Toronto, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Svitovyi Kongress Vil'nykh Ukraintsiv, Winnipeg, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Svoboda, Jersey City, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Tovarystvo opiky nad dit'my I moloddiu, Philadelphia, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Tovarystvo ukraintsiv samostiinykiv, Edmonton, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Towarzystwo Miłośników Jezyka Polskiego, Krakow, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Ukrainian American Association of University Professors, Philadelphia, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Ukrainian Literary and Arts Club in Edmonton, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Ukrainian Professional and Businessmen's Association, Edmonton, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Ukrainian Quarterly, New York, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Ukrainian Self-Reliance League: see Tovarystvo ukraintsiv samostiinykiv
    - Ukrains'ka Vil'na Akademiia Nauk (UVAN), New York, 1968 1976 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Ukrains'ke Students'ke Tovarystvo, Buffalo, 1972-1973 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Ukrains'ko-Shveds'ka kul'turna spilka, undated (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Ukrains'kyi Akademichnyi Kliub, Ottawa, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Ukrains'kyi Narodnyi Soiuz, Ink., Jersey City, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Ukrains’kyi Zasiv: see Subseries I.1: Bondar-Tereshchenko
    - Ulbandus Review: a Journal of Slavic Languages and Literature: see Subseries I.1: Naydan
    - United States Information Agency, Washington, DC, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Universitetsbiblioteket Uppsala, 1951 1971 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Alberta, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of California, 1959-1993 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Idaho, 1971-1974 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Mannitoba, Winnipeg, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, 1958 1964 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Ottawa, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University Palackeho v Olomouci, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, 1968 1975 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Pittsburgh, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Sheffield, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Southern California, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Texas, Austin, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Toronto, 1962-1988 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Washington Press, Seattle, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - University of Wisconsin Press, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Uriad Ukrains'koi Narodnoi Respubliki v Ekzyli, Resort kul'tury i nauky: see Subseries I.1: Zhyla
    - Winnipeg School Division No.1, 1974-1975 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - WRVR, New York, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Yale University, 1975-1977 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Yeshiva College, Yeshiva University, New York, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified Gymnasium in Ukraine, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 16)
- Series II: Writings, 1926-1990s
  The series comprises articles, monographs, papers presented at conferences and congresses, talks, memoirs, reviews, poetry, extensive research notes and drafts. Arranged in six subseries.
  - Subseries II.1: Memoirs "Ia - mene - meni", undated
    Typescript of memoirs.
    - Chastyna persha: Ukraina (Box 17, Folder 1 to 5)
    - Chastyna druha: Evropa (Box 17, Folder 6 to 8)
  - Subseries II.2: Articles and Monographs, 1929-1998
    Manuscripts, typescripts and galley proofs with holograph corrections and notes. Arranged alphabetically. Printed materials, books and reprints and off-prints, stored and listed separately from the manuscripts. Books with margin notes and inscription were cataloged to CLIO and remain in the collection.
    - Manuscripts, 1929-1998
      - "28 dniv osoblyvoi sluzhby sotsiialistichnii bat'kivshchyni i po tomu: buval'shchyna i nebuval'shchyna", New York, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - "Alexander Potebnja: an essay to reconstruct the integrity of his image", 1991 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - "Biohrafiia po smerti", undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - "Chy 'vs'o ravno'?"1944 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - "Cui bono? Mini-polemika" (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - "Do pytannia periodyzatsii istorii ukrains'koi movy", New York, 1996 (with related letters and notes) (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - "Dobri novyny z Kharkova", undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - "Funktsii rodovoho vidminku v ukrains'kii movi", 1929 (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - "Halychyna: peredmova", New York, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - "History of Slavic. Historical phonology of the Slavic languages: a brief outline of contents and methods" (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - [Hnizdovs'kyi], 1965 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - "Ho-Hai-Ho: Pro prozu Iuriia Andrukhovycha i z pryvodu", 1996 (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - "Iazyk i stil' romana F.M.Dostoevskogo 'Bednye liudi'", 1929 (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - "Istorychni perypetii odniiei syntaksychnoi konstruktsii u skhidnoslov'ians'kykh movakh: bezosobovi rechennia na -no/-mo iz znakh.vidminkom dodatka", 1969 (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - "Liudy Akademii, mury Akademii, knyhy Akademii: spohady i mirkuvannia z nahody p'iatdesiatykh rokovyn Ukrains'koi Vil'noi Akademii Nauk u SShA", 1995 (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - "Muscovite clerks face another country", undated (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - "Na iuvilei Mykoly Nakonechnoho", undated (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - "Na movni temy: lystky z bloknotu", undated (incompleted) (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - Narys suchasnoi ukrains'koi literaturnoi movy, Munich, 1951 (galley proof) (Box 18, Folder 19 to 22)
      - "Nikolaj Ge: an artist in a different context", 1989 (Box 19, Folder 1 to 3)
        - Typescripts and notes (Box 19, Folder 1 to 2)
        - "Mykola Ge i Taras Shevchenko: mystets' u vidminnomu konteksti" (translation by O.Solovei) (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - [Nitsshe], 1944 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - "Notatky pro etymolohiiu", 1936 (with Shevelov's note about this article, 1990) (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - "Novitnia Odisseia: mozhlyvosti i obmezhennia", 1994 (review on L.Bol'shakov's book about Shevchenko (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - "O kharaktere iazyka i stilia komedii Griboedova 'Gore ot uma': po materialu IV dejstviia", 1929 (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - "O.S.Pushkin u ukrains'kykh dorevoliutsiinykh perekladak: 1829-1917", undated (incomplete) (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - On Lunt's reviews:
        - "Few explanations for the readers of The Slavic and East European Journal", 1966 (Box 19, Folder 9)
        - To the Editors of Rocznik slawisstyczny, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
        - Untitled (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - "Pohliad na isotoriiu ukrains'koi literaturnoi movy 18-19 storichchia: Skovoroda-Shevchenko-Voronyi", undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - "Potebnia i standart ukrains'koi movy", 1991 (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - Prehistory of Slavic. The Historical phonology of common Slavic. Heidelberg, 1964 (galley proof) (Box 20, Folder 1 to 3)
      - "Pro chyslivnykovi konstruktsii i pro inshi rechi," 1996 (papers for 3-i mizhnarodnyi konhress ukrainistiv) (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - "Pro kryterii v pytanniakh ukrains'koho ofitsiinoho pravopysu", 1994 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - "Problemy pokhodzhennia ukrains'koi movy", undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - "Prolegomena do vyvchennia movy ta styliu H.Skovorody" (translated from English by Rostyslav Dotsenko), 1978 1994 (Box 20, Folder 7 to 8)
      - "Prolegomena to Studies of Skovoroda's Language and Style, 1994 (in English) (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - "Prosta cad and prostaja mova", New York, 1987 (typescript with holograph corrections) (Box 20, Folder 10 to 11)
      - "Pryntsypy i etapy bol'shevyts'koi movnoi polityky na Ukraini", undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - "Ravena", undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - "Recht auf Naivitat oder Jedermann's Programm in der Literatur: Aus franzosischen Neuerscheinungen", undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - [Skovoroda], 1944 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - "Slovo na vidkrytti Shostoi shevchenkoznavchoi konferentsii", 1986 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - "Some corrections in the traditional outline of the history of Russian", undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - "Taras Schewtschenko", undated (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - "Tours and detours of Ukrainian official spelling", 1994 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - [Tychyna], 1940-1941 (incomplete) (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - "U dovhii cherzi: Problemy reabilitatsii", New York, 1990 (paper presented at Konhress Mizhnorodnoi assotsiatsii ukrainistiv; with related letters and other materials) (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - "U ne-Rembrandtovii galerei avtoportretiv: Trylohiia peredmov, do nykh pisliamova, nichoho poseredyni", (with related letters) (Box 21, Folder 11)
      - "U nespokoi mysli", undated (Box 21, Folder 12)
      - "Ukrains'ka mova v sebe vdoma siohodni i zavtra", 1986 (Box 21, Folder 13)
      - [Ukrains'kyi pravopys], 1990s (Box 21, Folder 14)
      - "Vid Teofana Prokopovycha do Radishcheva: rysy "ideolohichnoho styliu" doby v rosiis'kii literature XVIII storichchia", 1949-1950 (Box 21, Folder 15)
      - "Volodymyr Mykhailovych. Kil'ka rys do portretu", undated (Box 21, Folder 16)
      - "Vsima hraniamy", undated (Box 21, Folder 17)
      - "Z oboru ukrajinske etymologie", 1969 (Box 21, Folder 18)
      - "Zahybel' propashchoho pokolinnia: shtrykhy z istorii literaturnoho vidrodzhennia dvadtsiatykh rokiv na Ukraini" (Box 21, Folder 19)
      - Untitled, various dates (including incomplete manuscript about Tychyna) (Box 21, Folder 20 to 25)
    - Books, 1948-1991 (with margin notes and inscriptions)
      - Historical phonology of the Ukrainian language, 1979 (Box 22)
      - In and around Kiev, 1991 (Box 22)
      - Neues Theater? Betrachtungen zur modernen Dramatik, 1948 (Box 22)
      - Prehistory of Slavic, 1964 (Box 22)
      - Syntax of modern literary Ukrainian, 1963 (Box 22)
      - Taras Sevcenko, 1814-1816. A symposium, 1962 (Box 23)
      - Teasers and appeasers, 1971 (Box 23)
    - Off-prints and reprints, 1940-1986
      - 1940-1957 Publications bound in two volumes (Titles are listed here in the same order as they appear in the volumes) (Box 23)
        - Volume 1:
          - "Towards historical dialectology: its delimitation of history of literary language", 1954 (Box 23)
          - "Probleme der Bildung des Zahlwortes als Redeteil in den slavischen Sprachen", 1953 (Box 23)
          - "Ueber die Besonderheiten der Sprache der Frauen", 1952 (Box 23)
          - Reviews. "Gunnar Herne. Die slawischen Farbenbenennungen; eine semasiologisch-etymologische Untersuchung"; "Horace G. Lunt. Old Church Slavonic grammar"; "L. Ladnik und R. Aitzetmuller. Handworterbuch zu den altkircshenslawischen Texten", 1957 (Box 23)
          - "Tr't' - type roups and problem of Moravian components in Old Church Slavonic, 1957 (Box 23)
          - "Ukrainien littéraire", 1956 (Box 23)
          - "On Slavic names for falls of Dnepr in "De Administrando Imperio" of Constantine porphyrogenitus", 1955 (Box 23)
          - Reviews. "Ad. Stender- Petersen. Varangica", 1954 (Box 23)
          - "Konsonanten vor e, i in den protoukrainischen Dialekten", 1956 (Box 23)
          - Review. "Cecilia Borelius. Safonovičs Chronik im Codex AD 10 der Västeråsen Gymnasialbibliothek. Eine sprachliche Untersuchung", 1952 (Box 23)
          - "Tradytsiia i novatorstvo v leksytsi i stylistytsi I. P. Kotliarevs'koho", 1940 (Box 23)
          - "Iz sposterezhen' nad movoiu suchasnoi poezii", 1940 (Box 23)
          - "Zur Frage der Ukrainisch - Weissruthenischen Sprachgrenze", 1953 (Box 23)
          - "Kost' Mychal'cuk (1841-1914) als Dialektologe", 1952 (Box 23)
          - Review. "Jar. Rudnyckyj. Die Lemberger Ukrainische Stadtmundart", 1943 (Box 23)
          - "Problems in Formation of Belorussian", 1953 (Box 23)
          - "Stefan Yavorsky and conflict of ideologies in age of Peter I", undated (Box 23)
          - "Edvard Strikha: History of literary mystification", 1955 (Box 23)
          - "Las tendencias en la literatura Ucraniana. Bajo el dominio de los Soviets", undated (Box 23)
        - Volume 2:
          - "Zum Problem der Satzgliederung und Aussonderung der Redeteile", 1952 (Box 23)
          - "Alexander Potebnja as linguist", 1956 (Box 23)
          - "Latent phoneme in making: affricate "з" in Slavic", 1955 (Box 23)
          - "Participium universale im Slavischen", 1953 (Box 23)
          - "New comparative grammar of Slavic languages", 1951 (Box 23)
          - "Important work in Ukrainian onomastics", 1952 (Box 23)
          - "Phonema Errans", 1950 (Box 23)
          - "Ukrainisches vantaž 'Ladung, Frachtgut, Last' and das Problem der 'Argot-Suffixe'", 1954 (Box 23)
          - "On Slavic language interrelations. Ukrainian influence on Polish language in 16th and 17th centuries", 1953 (Box 23)
          - "Коst' Mykhail'chuk", 1952 (Box 23)
          - "Study of Soviet Ukrainian literature", undated (Box 23)
          - "On Teofan Prokopovič as writer and preacher in his Kiev period", 1954 (Box 23)
          - Reviews. "Justina Besharov. Imagery of Igor' Tale in light of Byzantino-Slavic poetic theorym", 1956 (Box 23)
          - Reviews. "Československá Akademie Věd, Ústav pro jazyk český, Slovník staročeský, pracovní zásady a ukázky hesel", 1956 (Box 23)
          - Reviews. "Ján Stanislav. Dejiny slovenského jazyka i Úvod a hláskoslovie, 1956 (Box 23)
          - Reviews. "S. Westfal. Study in Polish morphology. Genitive Singular Masculine", 1956 (Box 23)
          - "Structure of root in modern Russian", 1957 (Box 23)
          - Review. "V. Vinogradov. Russkij jazyk. Grammatičeskoje učenie o slove", 1947 (Box 23)
          - "Styl' politychnoi liryky P.H.Tychyny", undated (Box 23)
          - "Vsevolod Hancov. Olena Kurilo", 1954 (Box 23)
        - Inclosures found in bound volumes of articles (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - 1952-1986 (in alphabetical order):
      - "Alternative analysis of some language features of 'Merilo pravednoje'", 1984 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - "Belorussian versus Ukrainian: delimitation of texts before A.D. 1569", 1974 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - "Boris O. Unbegaun. September 4, 1898-March 4, 1973", 1973 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - "Chronologie der Enstehung der ukrainischen Dialekte im Lichte der historischen Phonologie", 1978 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - "Dwie uwagi o slowianskim e", 1965 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - "E > 'O ou 'O > E Dans les langues slaves de l'est?" 1964 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - "Gospel of reims and the history of the Serbo-Croatian language", 1975 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - "'Grammatik der kleinrussischen Munhdart' von Pavlovskij und ihr Autor", 1958 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - "Iazyk nadpisei na kreste Evfrosinii Polotskoi 1161 goda i nekotorye soobrazheniia o iazyke Rusi XII veka", 1986 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - "Jesmi 'I am' and some verbal endings in Slavic", 1977 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - "Kirschenslavischen elemente in der modernen Russischen literatursprache", 1960 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - "Leonid Vasil'ev and his work", 1972 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - "Moravismen im Izbornik von 1076?" 1986 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - "Nazwiska slowianskie na -kevic", undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - "Omega in the Codex Hankenstein: a hitherto unnoticed episode in the Ukrainian development o>i", 1978 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "On predicaments, predictability and futurism in phonology", 1967 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "On the chronology of H and the new G in Ukrainian", 1977 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "On the history of a sound that has no history: F in the Ukrainian language", 1977 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "On the lexical make-up for the Galician-Volhynian chronicle: an experiment in the comprehensive study of vocabulary followed by a few remarks on the literary language of Old Rus'", 1968 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "On the polonisms in literary Ukrainian", 1975 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "On the problem of the participation of Y and I in the loss of Jers", 1976 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "On the so-called signature of Queen Ann of France (1063)", 1978 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "Open syllable languages and their evolution: Common Slavic and Japanese", 1969 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "Orzeczenia bezprodmiotowe odimieslowowe na -no, -to w jezyku polskim przed rokiem 1450", undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "Pokolinnia dvadtsiatykh rokiv v ukrains'komu movnoznavstvi", 1962 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - "Problem des ukrainischen Anteils an der Bildung der sussischen Schriftsprache Ende des 18. Jahrhunderts", 1970 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - "Probleme der Bildung des zahlwortes als redeteil in den slavischen sprachen", 1952 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - "Problems in the formation of Belorussian", 1953 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - "Prothetic consonants in Common Slavic", 1963 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - "Reader in the history of the Eastern Slavic Languages: Russian, Belorussian, Ukrainian", 1958 (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - "Remark on extra-systematic vowel length in Slavic: the cases of Ukrainian and Macedonian", 1985 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - "Remark on Intermedia dwoie published with Tragaedia albo wizerunk smierci Przeswietego Jana Chrzciciela Przeslanca Bozego by Jakub Gawatowic (1619)", 1981 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - "Some remarks on written records as a source of evidence for the historical phonology of the Middle Ukrainian language (1569-1720)", undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - "Tendency in language development: a remark on the erosion of the feminine i-stem substantives in the Ukrainian language", 1983 (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - "Ukrainische shcriftsprache:1798-1965", 1966 (Box 24, Folder 6)
      - "Vasyl' Mova (Lymans'kyi)", 1967 (Box 24, Folder 7)
      - "Vicissitudes of a syntactic construction in Eastern Slavic", 1969 (Box 24, Folder 7)
      - "Weak Jers in Serbo-Croatian and South Slavic: developments in the word initial syllable", 1965 (Box 24, Folder 8)
      - "Wechselwirkung von zwei Akzentuierungstypen der Partizipien Prateriti Passivi von Verben der 3. Klasse mit Infinitiv auf -at' in den slavischen Sprachen", 1962 (Box 24, Folder 8)
      - "Why in Ukrainian sl'ozy 'tear' but zelenyj 'green', while in Russian sljozy and zeljonyj? An unresolved problem of Ukrainian historical phonology", 1979 (Box 24, Folder 8)
      - "Z istorii ukrains'koho romantyzmu", 1966 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Subseries II.3: Reviews, 1940s-1990s (see also Subseries II.2: Articles and Monographs--Off-prints and reprints bound in two volumes, Box 23)
    Manuscripts and off-prints/reprints of reviews written by Shevel'ov. Manuscripts arranged alphabetically and printed reviews arranged in chronological order. Some reviews were bound along with articles and stored in Subseries II.2: Off-prints and reprints bound in two volumes.
    - Manuscripts, 1940s-1990s (in alphabetical order) (Box 24, Folder 9 to 15)
    - Off-prints and reprints, 1950s-1980s (in chronological order) (Box 24, Folder 16 to 19)
  - Subseries II.4: Fragments, undated
    Contains fragments of various writings.
    - Fragments of various writings (Box 25, Folder 1 to 4)
  - Subseries II.5: Poetry, 1926-1969
    Holograph manuscripts and typescripts of Shevel'ov's original poetry and translations.
    - Original poetry and translations (holograph manuscripts and typescripts) (Box 25, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Subseries II.6: Drafts, Notes, and Research Materials, 1930s-1990s
    Drafts and notes on various subjects including teaching courses, linguistics, personalia, philosophy, theatre, and others. Organized by subject in alphabetical order. Research materials include books summaries, bibliography on various subjects, and clippings.
    - Course outlines: (Box 25, Folder 7 to 8)
      - Polish language, undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
      - Ukrainian language, undated (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Linguistics, 1930s-1990s (lexis, syntax, phonology, spelling, punctuation, morphology, history of language. Arrange in alphabetical order) (Box 25, Folder 9 to 22)
    - Linguistics (cont.) (Box 26, Folder 1 to 20)
    - Personalia: (Box 27, Folder 1 to 13)
      - Barka (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Buzuk (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - Hnizdovs'kyi (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - Hulak-Artemovs'kyi: see Kvitka-Osnov'ianenko (Folder 7)
      - Iefremov (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - Koshelivets' (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Kostiuk (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Kotliarevs'kyi (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - Kryms'kyi (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - Kubiiovych (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - Kvitka-Osnov'ainenko (Box 27, Folder 7)
      - Shashkevych (see also Folder 11) (Box 27, Folder 8)
      - Shevchenko (Box 27, Folder 9 to 12)
      - Simovych (Box 27, Folder 13)
      - Stus (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Philosophy (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Theatre (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Various subjects (Box 27, Folder 16 to 19)
    - Various subjects (cont.) (Box 28, Folder 1 to 11)
    - Research materials:
      - Bibliography on various subjects (Box 28, Folder 12 to 17)
      - Books notes and summaries (Box 29, Folder 1 to 8)
      - Clippings (Box 29, Folder 9)
- Series III: Documents, Biographical and Background Materials, 1945-2000
  Documents include some MUR related documents and acknowledgement and certificate of 1990s. Biographical and background materials include articles about Shevel'ov, reviews on his writings, and bibliography of his works.
  - MUR Documents: By-law, list of members, [1945] (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Personal Documents: (Folder 11 to 13)
    - Acknowledgement for contribution to science, Kyiv, undated (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Certificate of election Shevelov as a foreign member of Ukrainian Academy of Sciences, Kyiv, 1991 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Addresses, notes (Box 29, Folder 13)
  - Biographical and Background Materials:
    - Articles about him, 1998-2000 (Box 29, Folder 14 to 16)
      - Chaban, L., A.Danylenko, E.Solovei. Foreword and biography for Iurii Volodymyrovych Shevel'ov (Iurii Sherekh): Materiialy do bibliohrafii. New York, 1998 (with Shevelov's notes) (Box 29, Folder 14)
      - Chumachenko, Anna. Iurii Sherekh i "Shosta symfoniia Mykoly Kulisha", undated (Box 29, Folder 15)
      - Danylenko, Andrii. "Iurii Sheveliov iak istoryk skhidnoslov'ians'kykh mov," 2000 (Box 29, Folder 15)
      - Kachurovs'kyi, Ihor. Radioscript dedicated to Shevel'ov's 75 anniversary, 1983 see Series I:Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Kachurovs'kyi (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Materials related to Shevelov's 90-year anniversary, 1998 (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Reviews on his writings, 1948-1998 (including enclosures found in the books):
      - Historical Phonology of the Ukrainian Language. Heidelberg, 1979 (by various authors) (Box 29, Folder 17)
      - In and around Kiev. Heidelberg, 1991 (Box 29, Folder 18)
      - Kirschenslavischen Elemente in der modernen russischen Literatursprache, 1960 (Box 29, Folder 19)
      - Neues Theater? Betrachtungen zur modernen Dramatic. Munich, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 20)
      - Prehistoric Slavic (Box 29, Folder 21)
      - Prehistory of Slavic: the historical phonology of Common Slavic (Box 29, Folder 22)
      - "Reader in the history of the Eastern Slavic languages: Russian, Belorussian, Ukrainian," 1958 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - Syntax of Modern Literary Ukrainian. The Simple Sentence. 1963 (by W.Svoboda) (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - Taras Shevchenko. 1814-1861. A Symposium, 1965 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - Ukrainian language in the first half of the twentieth century (1900-1941), 1989 (Box 30, Folder 2)